Ten years ago exactly,
قبل عشرة أعوام،
I was in Afghanistan.
كنتُ في أفغانستان،
I was covering the war in Afghanistan,
كنتُ أغطي مجريات الحرب في أفغانستان،
and I witnessed, as a reporter for Al Jazeera,
وشھدتُ كمراسل للجزيرة
the amount of suffering and destruction
حجمَ المعاناة والدمار.
that emerged out of a war like that.
الذي خلفَته تلك الحرب.
Then, two years later,
وبعد ذلك بعامين،
I covered another war -- the war in Iraq.
غطيتُ حربا أخرى، الحرب في العراق.
I was placed at the center of that war
لقد كنتُ في قلب أحداثھا،
because I was covering the war
لأني كنت أغطي مجرياتھا
from the northern part of Iraq.
من شمال العراق.
And the war ended
وانتھت الحرب
with a regime change,
بتغيير النظام،
like the one in Afghanistan.
كما حدث في أفغانستان.
And that regime
ذلك النظام
that we got rid of
الذي تخلصنا منه
was actually a dictatorship,
كان دكتاتوريا،
an authoritarian regime,
نظام استبدادي،
that for decades
الذي خلال عقود من الزمن،
created a great sense of paralysis
أحدثَ شعورا بالشلل
within the nation, within the people themselves.
داخل الأمة ونفوس الناس.
However,
ومع ذلك
the change that came through foreign intervention
فإن التغيير الذي جاء عبر التدخل الأجنبي،
created even worse circumstances for the people
أوجد للناس ظروفا أكثر سوءا،
and deepened the sense
وعمّق مشاعر الشلل
of paralysis and inferiority
وعقدة النقص
in that part of the world.
في ذلك الجزء من العالم.
For decades,
لقد عشنا على مدى عقود من الزمن
we have lived under authoritarian regimes --
في ظل أنظمة استبدادية
in the Arab world, in the Middle East.
في العالم العربي والشرق الأوسط.
These regimes
ھذه الأنظمة
created something within us during this period.
أوجدت شيئا في أنفسنا خلال تلك الفترة.
I'm 43 years old right now.
لقد بلغتُ الآن ثلاثة وأربعين عاما.
For the last 40 years,
وعلى مدى أربعين عاما،
I have seen almost the same faces
لم أشاھد سوى الوجوه ذاتھا
for kings and presidents ruling us --
من ملوك ورؤساء يحكموننا--
old, aged, authoritarian,
ھرمة واستبدادية،
corrupt situations --
فاسدة، أوضاع--
regimes that we have seen around us.
الأنظمة التي رأيناها حولنا.
And for a moment I was wondering,
وفي لحظة ما، كنتُ أتساءل:
are we going to live in order to see
ھل سنعيش حتى نرى
real change happening on the ground,
تغييرا حقيقيا يحدث على أرض الواقع؟
a change that does not come through foreign intervention,
تغييرا لا يأتي عبر التدخل الأجنبي
through the misery of occupation,
أو عبر مآسي الاحتلال،
through nations invading our land
أو عبر غزو دول لبلادنا
and deepening the sense of inferiority sometimes?
وتعميق مشاعر عقدة النقص أحيانا لدينا؟
The Iraqis: yes, they got rid of Saddam Hussein,
نعم، تخلّص العراقيون من صدام حسين،
but when they saw
ولكن عندما رأوا
their land occupied by foreign forces
أراضيھم تُحتل من قبل القوات الأجنبية
they felt very sad,
شعروا بالأسى الشديد،
they felt that their dignity had suffered.
شعروا بأن كرامتھم تعرضت للأذى.
And this is why they revolted.
ولھذا، ثاروا
This is why they did not accept.
ولم يقبلوا بذلك
And actually other regimes, they told their citizens,
وفي حقيقة الأمر، قالت أنظمة أخرى لمواطنيھا:
"Would you like to see the situation of Iraq?
ھل تريدون أن تشھدوا حالة عراقية في بلادكم؟
Would you like to see civil war, sectarian killing?
ھل تودون رؤية حرب أھلية وقتل طائفي؟
Would you like to see destruction?
ھل تريدون رؤية الدمار؟
Would you like to see foreign troops on your land?"
ھل تريدون رؤية قواتٍ أجنبيةً على أراضيكم؟
And the people thought for themselves,
عندھا، اعتقد الناس
"Maybe we should live with
أن الأفضلَ لھم أن يتعايشوا
this kind of authoritarian situation that we find ourselves in,
مع ھذا الوضع المستبد
instead of having the second scenario."
عوضَ أن يعيشوا السيناريو الآخر.
That was one of the worst nightmares that we have seen.
لقد كان ھذا من أسوأ الكوابيس التي شھدناھا.
For 10 years,
وعلى مدى عشرة أعوام،
unfortunately we have found ourselves
-لسوء الحظ- وجدنا أنفسنا
reporting images of destruction,
ننقل صور الدمار
images of killing,
وصور القتل
of sectarian conflicts,
والصراعات الطائفية
images of violence,
وصورالعنف
emerging from a magnificent piece of land,
من أھم بقاع الأرض
a region that one day was the source
التي كانت مصدرا
of civilizations and art and culture
للحضارة والفن والثقافة
for thousands of years.
على مدى آلاف السنين.
Now I am here to tell you
وأنا ھنا لأقول لكم
that the future
إن المستقبل
that we were dreaming for
الذي كنا نحلم به،
has eventually arrived.
بات أخيرا قابَ قوسين أو أدنى.
A new generation,
فجيل الشباب
well-educated,
المثقف
connected,
المتصل
inspired by universal values
والملھم بالقيم العالمية
and a global understanding,
والفھم الكوني،
has created a new reality for us.
خلق لنا واقعا جديدا.
We have found a new way
لقد وجدنا وسيلة جديدة
to express our feelings
للتعبير عن مشاعرنا
and to express our dreams:
والإفصاح عن أحلامنا.
these young people
فھؤلاء الشباب
who have restored self-confidence
أعادوا لشعوبنا الثقة بالنفس
in our nations in that part of the world,
في ذلك الجزء من العالم،
who have given us
ومنحونا
new meaning for freedom
معنى جديدا للحرية،
and empowered us to go down to the streets.
وشجعونا على النزول إلى الشوارع.
Nothing happened. No violence. Nothing.
لن يحدث شيء، لا عنف، لا تخريب.
Just step out of your house,
فقط اخرُجوا من منازلكم
raise your voice
وارفعوا أصواتكم
and say, "We would like to see the end of the regime."
بھتاف واحد "نريد إسقاط النظام".
This is what happened in Tunisia.
ھذا بالضبط ما حدث في تونس.
Over a few days,
وبعد أيام،
the Tunisian regime that invested billions of dollars
انھار النظام التونسي الذي استثمر مليارات الدولارات
in the security agencies,
في أجھزة أمنية
billions of dollars
مليارات الدولارات
in maintaining, trying to maintain,
للحفاظ على بقائه، الحفاظ على بقائه
its prisons,
وسجونه،
collapsed, disappeared,
انھار واختفى
because of the voices of the public.
بفضل صوت الشعب.
People who were inspired to go down to the streets
الناس الذين ألھموا أن يخرجوا إلى الشارع،
and to raise their voices,
ليرفعوا أصواتهم.
they tried to kill.
حاولوا قتلھم،
The intelligence agencies wanted to arrest people.
وعمد أفراد أجھزة المخابرات إلى اعتقال الناس،
They found something called Facebook.
ولكنھم وجدوا شيئا يدعى الفيسبوك
They found something called Twitter.
وجدوا شيئا يدعى تويتر.
They were surprised by all of these kinds of issues.
لقد فوجئوا بھذه الوسائل.
And they said,
وقالوا
"These kids are misled."
"إن ھؤلاء الفتيان مضلَّلون."
Therefore, they asked their parents
لذلك, طلبوا من أھاليھم
to go down to the streets
النزول إلى الشارع
and collect them, bring them back home.
وجمع وإعادة أبنائھم إلى منازلھم.
This is what they were telling. This is their propaganda.
ھكذا كانوا يقولون، وھذه ھي دعايتھم:
"Bring these kids home
"أعيدوا أبناءكم إلى بيوتكم
because they are misled."
لأنھم مضللون."
But yes,
ولكن، نعم،
these youth
ھؤلاء الشباب
who have been inspired
الملھمون
by universal values,
بالقيم العالمية،
who are idealistic enough
والمتمتعون بقدر كبير من المثالية
to imagine a magnificent future
لتصور المستقبل الرائع،
and, at the same time, realistic enough
وھم أيضا في الوقت نفسه واقعيون بما يكفي
to balance this kind of imagination
لتحقيق التوازن في ھذا النوع من التصور
and the process leading to it --
والعملية التي تقود إليه
not using violence,
فھم لا يستخدمون العنف،
not trying to create chaos --
ولا يحاولون خلق الفوضى.
these young people,
ھؤلاء الشباب
they did not go home.
لم يرجعوا إلى بيوتھم،
Parents actually went to the streets
وإنما خرج والديهم إلى الشوارع
and they supported them.
وقدموا لھم الدعم،
And this is how the revolution was born in Tunisia.
وھكذا ولدت الثورة في تونس.
We in Al Jazeera
ونحن في الجزيرة
were banned from Tunisia for years,
مُنعنا في تونس لسنوات
and the government did not allow
ولم تسمح الحكومة التونسية
any Al Jazeera reporter to be there.
بوجود أي مراسل للجزيرة على أراضيھا،
But we found that these people in the street,
ولكننا وجدنا أن جميع ھؤلاء الناس في الشارع
all of them are our reporters,
مراسلون لنا،
feeding our newsroom
يُغَذون غرفة الأخبار
with pictures, with videos
بالصور والفيديو
and with news.
والأخبار.
And suddenly that newsroom in Doha
وفجأة أصبحت غرفة الأخبار في الدوحة
became a center
مركزا يستقبل
that received all this kind of input from ordinary people --
كل تلك المدخلات من ناس عاديين
people who are connected and people who have ambition
طموحين ومتاوصلين
and who have liberated themselves
والذين حرروا أنفسھم
from the feeling of inferiority.
من مشاعر عقدة النقص.
And then we took that decision:
عندھا اتخذنا ذلك القرار:
We are unrolling the news.
بأننا نسير في الركب معكم
We are going to be the voice for these voiceless people.
سننقل صوت من لا صوت لھم،
We are going to spread the message.
وبأننا سننشر رسالتھم.
Yes, some of these young people
نعم، بعض ھؤلاء الشباب
are connected to the Internet,
على تواصل مع الإنترنت،
but the connectivity in the Arab world
ولكن ھذا التواصل في العالم العربي
is very little, is very small,
صغيرا وضئيلا جدا
because of many problems that we are suffering from.
بسبب العديد من المشاكل التي نعاني منھا.
But Al Jazeera took the voice from these people
غير أن الجزيرة حملت صوت الناس
and we amplified [it].
وأسمعناه للعالم.
We put it in every sitting room in the Arab world --
لقد نقلناه إلى كل غرفة جلوس في كل بيت في العالم العربي،
and internationally, globally,
وعالميا
through our English channel.
عبر قناتنا الناطقة بالإنجليزية.
And then people started to feel
ثم بدأ الناس يشعرون
that there's something new happening.
أن ثمة شيئا جديدا يحدث،
And then Zine al-Abidine Ben Ali
بعدھا قرر زين العابدين بن علي
decided to leave.
الرحيل.
And then Egypt started,
ثم بدأت مصر،
and Hosni Mubarak decided to leave.
وقرر حسني مبارك الرحيل أيضا.
And now Libya as you see it.
والآن ليبيا كما ترون.
And then you have Yemen.
ثم اليمن.
And you have many other countries trying to see
وغيرھا من الدول التي تحاول أن ترى
and to rediscover that feeling
وتستكشف ذلك النوع من الشعور
of, "How do we imagine a future
إزاء كيف يمكنُنا أن نتصور مستقبلا
which is magnificent and peaceful and tolerant?"
رائعا وھادئا ومتسامحا.
I want to tell you something,
أريد أن أقول لكم شيئا,
that the Internet and connectivity
إن الإنترنت والتواصل
has created [a] new mindset.
خلقا توجھا جديدا،
But this mindset
ولكن ھذا التوجه
has continued to be faithful
بقي مخلصا
to the soil and to the land
لتراب الأرض
that it emerged from.
التي نشأ فيھا.
And while this was the major difference
وھذا ھو الاختلاف الجوھري
between many initiatives before
بين العديد من المبادرات السابقة
to create change,
الرامية إلى إجراء التغيير.
before we thought, and governments told us --
في السابق، كنا نعتقد -كما كانت الحكومات تقول،
and even sometimes it was true --
وأحيانا كان ذلك صائبا-
that change was imposed on us,
أن التغيير فُرضَ علينا
and people rejected that,
فرَفضَه الناس،
because they thought that it is alien to their culture.
لأن ھذا التغيير غريب عن ثقافتھم
Always, we believed
كنا نعتقد دائما
that change will spring from within,
أن التغيير يجري من الداخل،
that change should be a reconciliation
وأن التغيير يجب أن ينسجم
with culture, cultural diversity,
مع ثقافتنا وتنوعنا الثقافي,
with our faith in our tradition
وإيماننا بتقاليدنا
and in our history,
وتاريخنا،
but at the same time,
ولكنه في الوقت نفسه
open to universal values, connected with the world,
يجب أن يكون منفتحا على القيم العالمية، ومرتبطا بالعالم
tolerant to the outside.
ومتسامحا مع الخارج.
And this is the moment
ھذه ھي اللحظة
that is happening right now in the Arab world.
التي يمر بھا العالم العربي،
This is the right moment, and this is the actual moment
وھذه ھي اللحظة المناسبة, وھذه ھي اللحظة الحقيقية
that we see all of these meanings meet together
التي نرى فيھا جميع ھذه المعاني تلتقي معا،
and then create the beginning
وتخلق البداية
of this magnificent era
لھذه الحقبة الرائعة
that will emerge from the region.
في تاريخ المنطقة.
How did the elite deal with that --
كيف تعاملتْ النخبةُ مع ذلك؟
the so-called political elite?
ما يسمونھا النخبةَ السياسية.
In front of Facebook,
فمقابل الفيسبوك,
they brought the camels in Tahrir Square.
جلبوا الجِمال في ميدان التحرير،
In front of Al Jazeera,
ومقابل الجزيرة
they started creating tribalism.
بدؤوا يثيرون النعرات القبَلية.
And then when they failed,
وعندما فشلوا،
they started speaking about conspiracies
شرعوا في الحديث عن المؤامرات
that emerged from Tel Aviv and Washington
التي تحاك في تل أبيب
in order to divide the Arab world.
وواشنطن لتقسيم العالم العربي.
They started telling the West,
لقد بدؤواا يقولون للغرب:
"Be aware of Al-Qaeda.
انتبھوا من القاعدة،
Al-Qaeda is taking over our territories.
إنھا تستولي على أراضينا،
These are Islamists
ھؤلاء إسلاميون
trying to create new Imaras.
يحاولون إقامة إمارات جديدة،
Be aware of these people
احذروا ھؤلاء الناس
who [are] coming to you
الذين يأتون اليكم
in order to ruin your great civilization."
لتدمير حضارتكم العظيمة.
Fortunately,
ولحسن الحظ،
people right now cannot be deceived.
أن الناس الآن لا يمكن خداعھم،
Because this corrupt elite
لأن ھذه النخبة الفاسدة
in that region
في المنطقة
has lost even the power of deception.
فقدَت حتى قوّتَھا في الخداع،
They could not, and they cannot, imagine
ولم تستطيع ولا بامكانها
how they could really deal with this reality.
ان تتصوّرَ كيفية التعامل مع ھذا الواقع.
They have lost.
لقد خسروا--
They have been detached
لقد انفصلت ھذه النخبة
from their people, from the masses,
عن شعوبھا وجماھيرھا،
and now we are seeing them collapsing
وھا نحن نراھم اليوم يتساقطون
one after the other.
واحدا تلو الآخر.
Al Jazeera is not
الجزيرة ليست
a tool of revolution.
أداة للثورة.
We do not create revolutions.
نحن لا نسھم في خلق الثورات.
However,
ولكن،
when something of that magnitude happens,
عندما يحدثْ شيءٌ من ھذا القبيل،
we are at the center of the coverage.
تجِدونا في قلب التغطية.
We were banned from Egypt,
لقد مُنعنا في مصر،
and our correspondents,
واعتُقل بعض مراسلينا،
But most of our camera people
ولكن معظم مصورينا
and our journalists,
وصحفيينا
they went underground in Egypt -- voluntarily --
عملوا في مصر سرا -- طوعا
to report what happened in Tahrir Square.
لينقلوا ما يحدث في ميدان التحرير.
For 18 days,
وعلى مدى 18 يوما،
our cameras were broadcasting, live,
كانت كاميرات التصوير تنقل بثا مباشرا
the voices of the people in Tahrir Square.
لأصوات المعتصمين في ميدان التحرير.
I remember one night
أتذكر في ذات ليلة،
when someone phoned me on my cellphone --
شخصا ما اتصل بي على ھاتفي الخلوي --
ordinary person who I don't know -- from Tahrir Square.
شخصا عاديا لا أعرفه-- من ميدان التحرير
He told me, "We appeal to you
وقال لي: أناشدكم
not to switch off the cameras.
أن لا توقفوا كاميرات التصوير،
If you switch off the cameras tonight,
لأنه إذا فعلتم ذلك الليلة،
there will be a genocide.
ستقع مجزرة.
You are protecting us
إنكم توفرون لنا الحماية
by showing what is happening at Tahrir Square."
عندما تظھرون ما يجري في ميدان التحرير.
I felt the responsibility
حينھا شعرتُ بمسؤوليتي
to phone our correspondents there
للاتصال بمراسلينا هناك
and to phone our newsroom
ليتصلوا بغرفة الأخبار
and to tell them, "Make your best
وقلت لھم: حاولوا قدر استطاعتكم
not to switch off the cameras at night,
أن لا تقفلوا عدسات الكاميرات بالليل،
because the guys there really feel confident
لأن الشباب ھناك يشعرون بالثقة عندما
when someone is reporting their story --
يقوم أحد ما بنقل أخبارھم،
and they feel protected as well."
ويشعرون كذلك بالحماية.
So we have a chance
لذلك لدينا فرصة
to create a new future
لبناء مستقبل جديد
in that part of the world.
في ذلك الجزء من العالم،
We have a chance
لدينا فرصة
to go and to think of the future
للتفكير بالمستقبل
as something which is open to the world.
كشيء منفتح على العالم.
Let us not repeat the mistake of Iran,
دعونا لا نكرر أخطاء إيران
of [the] Mosaddeq revolution.
ثورة مصدق،
Let us free ourselves -- especially in the West --
دعونا نحرر أنفسنا-- خاصة في الغرب--
from thinking about that part of the world
من التفكير في تلك البقعة من العالم
based on oil interest,
وفقا للمصالح النفطية
or based on interests
أو وفقا لمصلحة
of the illusion of stability and security.
الوھم بالاستقرار والأمن.
The stability and security
إن أمن واستقرار
of authoritarian regimes
الأنظمة المستبدة
cannot create
لا يوجد سوى
but terrorism and violence and destruction.
الإرھاب والعنف والدمار.
Let us accept the choice of the people.
دعونا نقبل باختيار الشعب،
Let us not pick and choose
دعونا لا ننتقي
who we would like to rule their future.
من نريد أن يحكم المستقبل،
The future should be ruled
فالمستقبل يجب أن تحكمه
by people themselves,
الشعوب بنفسھا.
even sometimes if they are voices
ورغم أن بعض الأصوات
that might now scare us.
التي ما زالت تخيفنا حتى الآن،
But the values of democracy
فإن قيم الديمقراطية
and the freedom of choice
وحرية الاختيار
that is sweeping the Middle East at this moment in time
التي تكتسح العالم العربي في الوقت الراھن،
is the best opportunity for the world,
ھي خير فرصة للعالم بأسره
for the West and the East,
-غربا وشرقا -
to see stability and to see security
كي يرى الاستقرار والأمن
and to see friendship and to see tolerance
والصداقة والتسامح
emerging from the Arab world,
تنبثق من العالم العربي،
rather than the images of violence and terrorism.
بدلا من صور العنف والإرھاب.
Let us support these people.
دعونا ندعم ھذه الشعوب،
Let us stand for them.
ونقف إلى جانبھا،
And let us give up
ونتخلى عن
our narrow selfishness
أنانيتنا الضيقة
in order to embrace change,
من أجل احتضان التغيير،
and in order to celebrate with the people of that region
ولكي نحتفل مع شعوب تلك المنطقة
a great future
بمستقبل رائع
and hope and tolerance.
وبالأمل والتسامح،
The future has arrived,
فالمستقبل قد وصل،
and the future is now.
والمستقبل ھو الآن.
I thank you very much.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
Chris Anderson: I just have a couple of questions for you.
كريس آندرسون: لدي فقط بضع أسئلة لك.
Thank you for coming here.
شكرا لحضورك إلى هنا.
How would you characterize the historical significance
كيف تصف الأھمية التاريخية
of what's happened?
لما يحدث؟
Is this a story-of-the-year, a story-of-the-decade
ھل ھي قصة العام، أم قصة العقد،
or something more?
أم شيء آخر؟
Wadah Khanfar: Actually, this may be the biggest story that we have ever covered.
وضاح خنفر: في الحقيقة، ربما ھذه أكبر قصة قمنا بتغطيتھا.
We have covered many wars.
لقد غطينا عدة حروب
We have covered a lot of tragedies, a lot of problems,
والعديد من المآسي والمشاكل،
a lot of conflict zones, a lot of hot spots in the region,
ومناطق النزاع، والعديد من المناطق الساخنة
because we were centered at the middle of it.
لأننا نقع في وسطھا،
But this is a story -- it is a great story; it is beautiful.
ولكن ھذه القصة عظيمة وجميلة،
It is not something that you only cover
فھي ليست قصة تود تغطيتھا فقط
because you have to cover a great incident.
لأنھا تشكل حدثا كبيرا،
You are witnessing change in history.
بل إنك تشھد تغييرا في التاريخ،
You are witnessing the birth of a new era.
و تشھد ميلاد حقبة جديدة،
And this is what the story's all about.
وھذا كل ما في الأمر.
CA: There are a lot of people in the West
ك أ: ھناك العديد من الناس في الغرب
who are still skeptical,
ما زالوا يشكون
or think this may just be an intermediate stage
أو يفكرون بأن ھذه مرحلة
before much more alarming chaos.
ما قبل فوضى عارمة،
You really believe
فھل تعتقد
that if there are democratic elections in Egypt now,
أنه إذا ما جرت انتخابات ديمقراطية في مصر،
that a government could emerge
ستعمل الحكومة المقبلة
that espouses some of the values you've spoken about so inspiringly?
على حماية القيم الديمقراطية التي تحدثتَ عنھا؟
WK: And people actually,
و خ: في الواقع،
after the collapse of the Hosni Mubarak regime,
بعد انھيار نظام حسني مبارك،
the youth who have organized themselves
الشباب الذين نظموا أنفسھم
in certain groups and councils,
ضمن جماعات معينة ومجالس
they are guarding the transformation
ھم من حمَى عملية التحول،
and they are trying to put it on a track
وحاولوا أن يضعوھا في مسار
in order to satisfy
يتوافق مع
the values of democracy,
قيم الديمقراطية،
but at the same time
وفي نفس الوقت
also to make it reasonable
ليجعلوھا معقولة
and to make it rational,
وليجعلوھا منطقية
not to go out of order.
بحيث لا تخرج عن السيطرة.
In my opinion, these people are much more wiser
من وجھة نظري، ھؤلاء الشباب أكثر حكمة
than, not only the political elite,
ليس من النخبة السياسية وحسب،
even the intellectual elite, even opposition leaders
بل من النخبة المثقفة وحتى قادة المعارضة
including political parties.
بمن فيھم الأحزاب السياسية.
At this moment in time, the youth in the Arab world
وفي ھذا الوقت بالذات، الشباب في العالم العربي
are much more wiser
أكثر حكمة
and capable of creating the change
وقدرة على إجراء التغيير
than the old --
من الكبار
including the political and cultural
بمن فيھم الأنظمة الثقافية والسياسية
and ideological
والأيدولوجية
old regimes.
البالية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
CA: We are not to get involved politically and interfere in that way.
ك أ: نحن لسنا بصدد أن نشارك في الجانب السياسي، أو أن نتدخل بذلك الشكل،
What should people here at TED,
ولكن ما الذي يتعيّن على الناس ھنا في ،TED
here in the West,
وھنا في الغرب-
do if they want to connect or make a difference
أن يفعلوا كي يتواصلوا ويتفاعلوا
and they believe in what's happening here?
اذا هم مئمنون بما يجري؟
WK: I think we have discovered a very important issue in the Arab world --
و خ: أعتقد أننا اكتشفنا أمرا في غاية الأھمية في العالم العربي،
that people care,
وھو أن الناس يھتمون
people care about this great transformation.
بھذا التحول العظيم،
Mohamed Nanabhay who's sitting with us,
محمد ناناباي، وهو معنا هنا،
the head of Aljazeera.net,
مدير موقع الجزيرة نت الإنجليزي،
he told me that a 2,500 percent increase
قال لي إنه ارتفعت نسبة
of accessing our website
الدخول إلى الموقع 2500 %
from various parts of the world.
في مختلف أرجاء العالم،
Fifty percent of it is coming from America.
وكان 50 % منھا في الولايات المتحدة،
Because we discovered that people care,
لأننا اكتشفنا أن الناس يبالون
and people would like to know --
ويريدون أن يعرفوا.
they are receiving the stream through our Internet.
فھم يستقبلون البث عبر موقعنا الإلكتروني.
Unfortunately in the United States,
لسوء الحظ، في الولايات المتحدة،
we are not covering but Washington D.C. at this moment in time
تغطيتنا تقتصرعلى واشنطن العاصمة حاليا
for Al Jazeera English.
وعبر القناة الناطقة بالإنجليزية.
But I can tell you, this is the moment to celebrate
ولكن أستطيع أن أقول لكم إن ھذه اللحظة ھي لحظة الاحتفال
through connecting ourselves
عبر تواصلنا
with those people in the street
مع أولئك الناس في الشارع،
and expressing our support to them
والتعبير عن دعمنا لھم،
and expressing this kind of feeling, universal feeling,
والتعبير عن ھذا الشعور العالمي
of supporting the weak and the oppressed
لدعم الضعفاء والمقموعين
to create a much better future for all of us.
من أجل بناء مستقبل أفضل للجميع.
CA: Well Wadah, a group of members of the TED community,
ك أ: حسنا السيد وضاح، هناك مجموعة من أعضاء من جماعة TED
TEDxCairo,
"TEDx القاهرة"
are meeting as we speak.
يلتقون ونحن نتحدث،
They've had some speakers there.
ولديهم بعض المتحدثين هناك.
I believe they've heard your talk.
أعتقد أنهم سمعوا ما تحدثت به.
Thank you for inspiring them and for inspiring all of us.
شكرا لإلهامهم وإلهامنا كلنا.
Thank you so much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)